Guide to the Secular Yiddish Schools in North America Collection M0732
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 1. Yiddish school files
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Hebrew Ando Finkerfeld. Kushi Dubon ve-od. Hotsaat B. Berloy: Tel Aviv. B. Havivi ve-A. Keren-Tal. Moadim li-Simha: Shavout ("matana li-yeled bi-kita 'gimel'). Kiryat Sefer: Yerushalaim, 1943. Hebrew children's book, fragment: Meurot Dubon ve-Miri be-yaar. Hebrew children's book, fragment. Keren Kayemet birthday certificate. Assorted materials., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Flashcards., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Flashcards., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Literature. Sholem Aleichem and Mimi Mahler. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Flashcards., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Rak, Gitl. Administrative/Organizational Materials. Registration Materials and note to parents re homework. AR/WC. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Rak, Gitl. Affiliated Organizations: Documents, AR/WC Schools: Program materials for branches and parent organizations. Includes curriculum materials, history of AR/WC schools, draft constitution, information on schools in NY area. English. No date. Also: Arbeter-ring heym far eltere mitglider - organizatsions komitet. Yiddish. Also: Course in Yiddish Stenography given by Sore Lieberson at Jewish Teachers Seminary and People's University in NY, mid-1940s. Later published. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Rak, Gitl. Creative Arts. Coloring-book materials, Biblical and family themes. English., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Rak, Gitl. Examinations: Elementary and High School. Bible, Jewish history, Yiddish literature, Israel, Yiddish language. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Rak, Gitl. Holiday Materials. Tu b'Shvat, Di mayse fun Purim, AR/WC 1946. Yiddish. Third Seder hagode (mimeographed), no date. Miscellaneous Pesach and Chanukah materials, Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Hebrew. Kalmen Bakhrakh, Ha-sefer. No date., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Holocaust. Mimeo "gedenk" with song. Yiddish. No date., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Israel. Ditto, 28th anniversary of birth of State of Israel (1976). Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Jewish History. Ditto "Ezra ha-soyfer". Yiddish. Booklet, Philip Kolko and Gloria Reich, "Rashi." No date. English., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Word-lotto spelling, alef-beys. Yiddish. Yudl Mark, "Heft far yidish in tsveytn lern-yor," 1956. Jewish Education Committee of NY. D. Bridger, "Arbeter-bukh tsum onheyber," 1967. Wolf and Sylvia Younin, "Lomir lernen yidish." AR/WC 1973., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Yiddish flashcards (drawings and words). Organized by holidays. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Yiddish flashcards (drawings and words). Organized by holidays. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Rak, Gitl. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Yiddish flashcards (drawings and words)., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Rak, Gitl. Publications for Children., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - Rak, Gitl. School Publicity. Meyer London WC School announcement, Passover Seder. Request for contributions. English. No date., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Rak, Gitl. Songs: Music and Lyrics. Various. M. Gelbart, "lomir kinder zingen." Yiddish. 1952., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Rak, Gitl. Tributes, Speeches, Anniversary Celebrations. Graduation speech. Yiddish. No date., Accession no. 1997-272 (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language. Mlotek, Yoysef. yidish kinder alef. Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, 1959. Efron (Yefroikin), S, and Yudel Mark. yidishe kinder. lernbukh farn tsveytn lernyor. Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, 1955-56. Yefroikin, Z. and Yudel Mark, a trit foroys.. Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, 1953., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Literature., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    Kaminsky, J., Lola. Mayses fun a meydele vos iz geven andersh. Workmen's Circle/AR, 1951 -- Pictures and poems. Yiddish. No cover, no author, leyenbikher far der idisher shul. No publisher, place or date. Vaynman, I., di bobetse mit di eyniklekh. Jewish School Publishing Assoc.: Montreal, 1945. No author, vos toyg azoyne feygl? Song and pictures. Mimeograph. New York, 1967. Betman, B., di flig. Yidishe folk-shuln un perets-shuln: Montreal: 1973. Picture, poems, glossary, music, games. Five pamphlets: Shtern, Y. berele un dos hintele, and der nasi hilel. Yud, N., der feter elye. Shtaynbarg, E. di ku un di kukavke, Kopelovitch-Hofman, L. dem zeydns tabik-pushke. All pamphlets Farlag Yidish Shul: Montreal, 1946. Yiddish.
  - Roth, Chane. School and Affiliated Organization Newsletters. Kulòtur un lebn (New York, N.Y.) Kulòtur un lebn = Culture and life. -- New York: Workmen's Circle, Accession no. 1997-255 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    Handmade vocabulary cards and sentence charts with questions and activities on the back. Yiddish.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Pictures with questions and activities written on the back. Yiddish.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    Hand-bound short-story booklets. Song cards. Olitsky, M. in der heym. Poems. Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, no date. Krishtalka, Sh. gut morgn. Basic sentences and pictures. Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, 1975. Dunsky, Sh. mayn lider bikhele: alef un beys. Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, no date. Gronman, S., shloyme hamelekh un der shuster. Play with songs. Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, 1972. Sigal, G., der karge un der kinig shloimeh. Comic book with questions, exercises and glossary. Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, 1972. Dittos, body parts and clothing. Notes about songs in the classroom. Yiddish.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    Handmade folders with song texts inside. Yiddish.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    Mlotek, Y. Yidishe kinder alef. Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, 1971.. Mlotek, Y. Yidishe kinder alef. Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, 1959. Efron (Yefroikin), S, and Yudel Mark. yidishe kinder beys. AR, republished by Jewish People's Schools and Peretz Schools: Montreal, 1961? Loose pages from a children's textbook. Yiddish.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Yiddish Language. Mark, Y.. heft far yidish in tveytn lernyor beys. Jewish Education Committee: New York, 1955. Bridger, D. ``arbets-buch''. Farlag Matones: New York: 1955-58. Mark, Y. arbets-bukh tsu `yidishe kinder alef'. Includes music, songs and exercises. Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, 1959. Fishman, G. sholem aleykhem, kinder. Jewish Education Committee: New York, no date. Alphabet charts for Mlotek, Y, yidishe kinder alef., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Hebrew. Eydlshteyn, M., et al. alef. and workbook Aleph Press: New York, 1954. Persky, E. ani lomed: khumash. S. Rabinowitz: New York, 1953. Bachrach, K. meah p'amim v'ekhat. Ayelet Press: New York, 1937. Rosen, A. Hebrew Self-Taught. Achiasaf: Jerusalem, 1969. Shachter, H. An English Companion to Part 2 of Ben-Shefer, Y., and A. Rosen ``elef milim.'' Achiasaf: Jerusalem, 1955. Copies of Hebrew weekly for beginners, Lamatchil, 1971., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Hebrew. Cais, J., and P. Enoch. Habet Ushma and teacher's guide. Chilton: Philadelphia, 1966. Sharfsheyn, Z. ameynu. Shiloh: New York, 1941., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Material: Hebrew. Charts for learning to tell time in Hebrew and for possessive endings. Educational Dept., Jewish National Fund. Furst, E. Yom-Yomi. Jonathan David: New York, 1957. Yofe, B. Mikhael, ha-kelev, he-khatul, v'ha-yona. Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, no date., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo. Boards and cards., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo. Cards., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo. Cards., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo. Cards., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish lotto. Heym un shul farayn, Yidishe folks shuln un Perets shuln, Montreal [1 of 2], 1972; Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish lotto. Heym un shul farayn, Yidishe folks shuln un Perets shuln, Montreal [2 of 2], 1972; Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Yiddish bingo. Cards., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Flashcards and picture/word cards with chits for games [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Flashcards and picture/word cards with chits for games [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Flashcards and picture/word cards with chits for games., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo. Cards. [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo. Cards. [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Curriculum Materials for Teachers. ``Teacher's Guide to `The Life of Rabbi Akiba'''. Yeshiva University Audio-Visual Service, 1953. ``A Nation Reborn.'' Educational Dept. of Jewish National Fund, England. After 1968. ``The Life of Our People.'' Pamphlet, Educational Dept. of Jewish National Fund, England. No date., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Affiliated Organizations: Documents., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    Official Opening, Samuel Bronfman House (1919-1969), Commemorating Fifty Years of Service by the Canadian Jewish Congress. Montreal, May 24, 1970. -- Shirayim, Newsletter of the Canadian Union of Jewish Students, ` Aug. 1972. English. -- Background Paper, Conference Canadian Jewish Congress, Eastern Region, Montreal, Jan. 28., 1973. -- Leaflet concerning rally for speech by Esther Markish, widow of Peretz Markish. Bilingual: French and English. Jan. 28, 1973. -- Deklaratsiye fun montrealer komitet far yidish to the First National Conference for Jewish Education. Montreal, 1972.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Literature. Mimeographed poem, Nokhem Yud, ``sof zumer.'' Yiddish., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Israel. Y. Burla, ``Hertsls kholem.'' Malke Lee, ``Teodor Hertsl.'' Mimeo poem, ``Lomir Yisroel bagrisn'' and ``Yom Hatzmaut.'' Yiddish., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Tributes, Speeches and Anniversary Celebrations. Folksbiene performance in honor of 50th anniversary of Peretz Schools. Montreal, 1964., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Souvenir Journals. ``Tslilim-klangen.'' Peretz Schools, Montreal, 1976., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Biographical Material., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    Cover letter from F. K. Wisener to Sara Timby. Curriculum vitae of Shifre Shtern Krishtalke, her mother. Both in English. Articles about and by Shifre Shtern Krishtalka. Yiddish.
    Biographical Material
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Holidays [1 of 3], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    ``Purim iz a shpil aza,'' Purim play with songs and glossary. Yiddish. -- Sema Davang, ``Sukes-freyd.'' Home and School Association, Jewish People's Schools and Peretz Schools: Montreal, 1972. Yiddish. No author, ``Shvues.'' .'' Home and School Association, Jewish People's Schools and Peretz Schools: Montreal, 1972. Yiddish. Folder, no author, ``Pesakh.'' Youth and Hechalutz Dept., World Zionist Org. Jerusalem, 1972. English. Pamphlet, ``Pesakh.'' Prepared by Shifre Krishtalka. Home and School Association, Jewish People's Schools and Peretz Schools: Montreal, 1975. ``Tu B'Shvat.'' JPPS Resource Center, Home and School Association, Jewish People's Schools and Peretz Schools: Montreal, 1973. English. Mimeo unbound, ``Di fir kashes.'' Yiddish. Handmade books for Pesakh, Khanike and Shabes.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Holidays [2 of 3], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Holidays [3 of 3], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Handmade books with stories and questions for students. Word charts? Yiddish.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Songs: Music and Lyrics. Handmade book, ``Bulbes.'' 1967., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo [1 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Games. Yiddish bingo [2 of 2], Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Curriculum Materials for Teachers, no. 1. Yiddish program for classes 1 and 2 [1 to 2], 1971; Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    Includes list of songs for course.
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Curriculum Materials for Teachers, no. 1. Yiddish program for classes 1 and 2 [2 to 2], 1971; Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Curriculum Materials for Teachers, no. 2. Yiddish program for classes 1 and 2 [1 of 2], 1971; Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Curriculum Materials for Teachers, no. 2. Yiddish program for classes 1 and 2 [2 of 2], 1971; Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Wisener, Freydl Krishtalka for Shifre Krishtalka. Curriculum Materials for Teachers, no. 3. Peretz School curriculum for class 2. 1943-44., Accession no. 1998-124 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Weinberg, Mort. Pedagogical Material: Hebrew. Rubenstein, Simha. Elements of Hebrew. Book One. Pamphlet 3. Bureau of Jewish Education: New York, 1938., Accession no. 1998-134 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Weinberg, Mort. Pedagogical Material: Hebrew. Yiddish workbook, Accession no. 1998-134 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Cassedy, Ellen. Pedagogical Material: Rituals and Lifecycle Events. Bas/bat mitsva of Margaret Cassedy held on Apr. 4, 1998. Contains Yiddish elements. Sent by her mother Ellen Cassedy with explanatory letter., Accession no. 1998-136 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Diploma. Arbeter Ring elemental-shul, 15 June 1947, for Feygl Berman. Photocopy. Yiddish., Accession no. 1998-137 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Diploma. Arbeter Ring mitlshul, 17 June 1951, for Feygl Berman. Photocopy. Yiddish., Accession no. 1998-137 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Photograph. Graduating class, Arbeter Ring elemental-shul, summer, 1947.; Accession no. 1998-137; Photocopy. (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Souvenir Journal. Annual journal, Bronx Arbeter Ring shul 16, June 1945; Accession no. 1998-137 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    Original. Yiddish and English.
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Souvenir Journal. Annual journal, Bronx Arbeter Ring shul 16, June 1946.; Accession no. 1998-137 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Souvenir Journal. Annual journal, Bronx Arbeter Ring shul 16, June 1947; Accession no. 1998-137 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Lynn, Florette, for Mary O. Berman. Souvenir Journals. Annual journal, Bronx Arbeter Ring shul 16, June 1952; Accession no. 1998-137 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Burstein, Norman. Souvenir Journal. Sholem Aleichem Folkshul 15, Brooklyn., June 1961, June 1968, June 1969; Accession no. 1998-138 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    June 1961 (2 copies), June 1968 (2 copies), June 1969. Original. Yiddish.
  - Burstein, Norman. Affiliated Organizations: Documents. Newsletter of Sholem Aleichem Folks Institute., Nov./Dec. 1971, May/June 1972, Nov./Dec. 1972.; Accession no. 1998-138 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    Original. Yiddish.
  - Burstein, Norman. Souvenir Journals., Accession no. 1998-138 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    Jubilee, 50th Anniversary of Sholem Aleichem Schools. New York, May 1963. Original. Yiddish and English. Also 20th Anniversary of the Congress for Jewish Culture. New York, 1968. Yiddish. Also calendar printed by Workmen's Circle Kovler Branch 475 (organized Oct. 1908), New Yor, 1967. English.
  - Burstein, Norman. Personal Correspondence. Sholem Aleichem Folkshul andandx0023;15 stationery and envelopes. Announcements of various events, 1950s-1970s. Yiddish and Yiddish/English., Accession no. 1998-138 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    Also Invitations to events sponsored by Sholem Aleichem Cultural Club, 1950s-1970s. Yiddish and Yiddish/English. Personal correspondence to Esther Burstein, Yiddish and English. Leaflet from Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring Progressive Kovler Young Friends Branch 475 (Bronx), 1924, announcing a special meeting. Yiddish. List of names including various school addresses, New York and New Jersey. Date unknown; before 1950s. English.
  - Burstein, Norman. Personal Correspondence. Letters to Esther Burstein. Yiddish. Photocopy of Sholem Aleichem Folkshul journal, 1937., Accession no. 1998-138 (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Daitz, Miriam K. Photographs. 2 photocopies of class photos. Includes letter to Gella Fishman with list of names of most children. No identification of when, where or what school., Accession no. 1998-139 (Box 37, Folder 12)
  - Hocky, Fay. Books. D. Bridger, Der onheyber. Farlag Matones: New York, 1947. H. Barkan, Amol iz geven [stories and legends]. Farlag Arbeter Ring: New York, 1945. H. Barkan, Kinder [stories]. Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring Education Dept., New York, 1951. M. Gelbart, ed. Zing mit mir. Lider far heym, shul, yontoyvim un fayerungen. Farlag Arbeter Ring: New York, 1945. Sh. Simon, Roberts ventures. Farlag Matones: New York, 1938. Z. Yefroikin and Y. Mark, Yidishe kinder beyz. Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring Education Dept.: New York, 1961. Yiddish., Accession no. 1998-254 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Miller, Betty Chafets. Souvenir Journals. I.L. Peretz School, Windsor, Ontario, Canada, 6/13/43.; Accession no. 1998-255 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    Contains information concerning the Peretz School philosophy and the importance of Yiddish language; also ads and notice of school play. Yiddish and English. --Graduation speech. I.L. Peretz School, Windsor, Ontario, Canada, "Vos di shul hot mir gegebn." Handwritten original; Yiddish w/ correction s in red. By Khane Kh[a]f[e]ts. Graduating class 1940-41. --Diploma, I.L. Peretz elementary school. June 1942. For Khane Khafets. Yiddish. --Photograph. Graduating class 1941-42, I.L. Peretz School. Names of students on back. Yiddish.
  - Langmann, Ann. Souvenir Journals. Jewish Cultural School of Nassau (Long Island, NY). Graduation 1974. Contains information re school philosophy and curriculum. Essays by and photos of graduates and students. Yiddish and English. IWO origins?, Accession no. 1998-256 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Kadar, Naomi P. Informational Material: History, Philosophy, Curriculum of Schools., Accession no. 1998-258 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    N. Kadar, "Yiddish in the Secular Jewish School Today. An Ethnographic Study." Master's thesis, Columbia Univ., Feb. 1996. Table of contents, endnotes, bibliography. English.
  - Wolfthal, Diane. Diplomas. Arbeter Ring nursery school, 1954. English. Arbeter Ring shul 3, 1958. Yiddish. Arbeter Ring elemental shul, 1961., Accession no. 1998-259 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Wolfthal, Diane -Yiddish. Certificate of promotion, 1959. Yiddish. 2 bilingual song sheets. Graduation program, 1961. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1998-259 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Sherman, Revka. [all in one folder]. Souvenir Journals. Graduation journals, 1970, 1971, 1972; Accession no. 1998-260 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    "niu yorker yidishe mitlshul." 1971 journal includes handwritten Yiddish speech addressed to friends of the mitlshul.